CARLOS HENRIQUE DE OLIVEIRA																																												
"DIFFERENT RATIOS OF ARGININE: LYSINE ON PERFORMANCE, SKIN"																																												
QUALITY AND CREATINE LEVELS OF BROILER CHICKENS FED DIETS REDUCED IN PROTEIN CONTENT																																												
Dissertation submitted to the Animal Science																																												
Graduate Program of the Universidade Federal de Viçosa in partial fulfillment of the requirements for the degree of Magister Scientiae.																																												
Adviser: Luiz Fernando Teixeira Albino.																																												
Co-adviser: Arele Arlindo Calderano																																												
VIÇOSA - MINAS GERAIS																																												
2022																																												
Ficha catalográfica elaborada pela Biblioteca Central da Universidade																																												
Federal de Viçosa - Campus Viçosa																																												
"T
Oliveira, Carlos Henrique de, 1992-
O48d                 Different ratios of arginine: lysine on performance, skin 2022         quality and cratine levels of broiler chickens fed diets reduced in
protein content / Carlos Henrique de Oliveira. – Viçosa, MG, 2022.
1 dissertação eletrônica (34 f.): il.
Texto em inglês. Inclui anexo.
Orientador: Luiz Fernando Teixeira Albino.
Dissertação (mestrado) - Universidade Federal de Viçosa, Departamento de Zootecnia, 2022.
Referências bibliográficas: f. 25-28.
DOI: https://doi.org/10.47328/ufvbbt.2022.533 Modo de acesso: World Wide Web.
1. Frango de corte - Alimentação e rações. 2. Arginina.
3. Lisina. I. Albino, Luiz Fernando Teixeira, 1953-.
II. Universidade Federal de Viçosa. Departamento de Zootecnia. Mestrado em Zootecnia. III. Título.
CDD 22. ed. 636.0855"																																												
Bibliotecário(a) responsável: Euzébio Luiz Pinto CRB-6/3317																																												
To my family.																																												
ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS																																												
To my parents Maria Aparecida da Silva Oliveira and Carlos Roberto de																																												
Oliveira who gave me their support during the postgraduate course.																																												
"To the Universidade Federal de Viçosa, for the opportunity to complete the postgraduate course."																																												
To my sisters Jocasta de Oliveira Melo and Esthela Graciele Oliveira who encouraged my decisions.																																												
To my girlfriend Kelly Morais Maia Dias who has always been by my side through the best and worst of moments.																																												
To my adviser Luiz Fernando Teixeira Albino who made me feel very welcome and made me grow professionally.																																												
To my co-adviser Arele Arlindo Calderano who encouraged me begin to the postgraduate course.																																												
To my friends Gustavo Rodrigues and Romário Bernardes who supported me during the postgraduate course.																																												
To Ramalho Rodrigueiro with whom I developed a project which made me grow professionally.																																												
"To my colleagues Artur, Kaique, Tobias, Renan, Bruno, Samuel, Pedro, Maria Rita, Condé, Eduardo, Fabossi, Hallef, Ideraldo, Thiago, Rosa, Rafael, Raully, Maurílio, Bruna, Rodrigo, Matheusão, André, Seu Carlos, Gilberto, João Ponte Nova, Adriano, Zé Lino, Daniel e Elisson that I have had the pleasure of working."																																												
"To the Fundação de Amparo à Pesquisa do Estado de Minas Gerais (FAPEMIG), for granting the scholarship."																																												
To  the  Coordenação  de  Aperfeiçoamento  de  Pessoal  de  Nível  Superior																																												
"(CAPES), to granting the scholarship."																																												
“Constantly think about how you could be doing things																																												
better and questioning yourself”.																																												
(Elon Musk)																																												
ABSTRACT																																												
"OLIVEIRA, Carlos Henrique de, M.Sc., Universidade Federal de Viçosa, August, 2022."																																												
"Different ratios of arginine: lysine on performance, skin quality and creatine levels of broiler chickens fed diets reduced in protein content. Adviser: Luiz Fernando Teixeira Albino. Co-adviser: Arele Arlindo Calderano."																																												
Two trials were carried out to assess different ratios of digestible arginine: lysine on																																												
"growth performance, skin quality and creatine levels in muscle and serum of broiler chickens fed diets reduced in protein content. A total of 1,540 Cobb500™ male chickens were used in each trial, and were distributed into 7 treatments, with 10 replicates with 22 birds each. The experimental diets were based on corn and soybean meal, and a control diet was formulated to satisfy broiler nutritional requirements. A basal diet with reduced protein content was formulated to meet broiler nutritional requirements, except for SID Arg levels. The experimental diets were obtained by adding L-arginine to basal diets, meeting six different SID Arg:Lys ratios (94, 100, 106, 112, 118 and 124%). Body weight, body weight gain, average daily feed intake, and feed conversion ratio were evaluated from 01 to 21 days old (trial 1) and from 22 to 44 days old (trial 2). At 21 and 44 days, in trials 1 and 2, respectively, birds were slaughtered to assess skin thickness (ST), skin strength (SS), creatine level in muscle (CRM) and serum (CRS). Data were subjected to ANOVA, and treatments were compared to the control group by Dunnett’s test (P≤0.05). Regression analyses were performed to model the variables assessed and the ratios of SID Arg: Lys. The SID Arg: Lys ratios did not affect ADFI of broilers in both trials (P>0.05), whereas it linearly increased the BW, BWG, and ST, in both trials (P<0.001). The FCR of broilers linearly decreased, in trial 1 (P = 0.038) and trial 2 (P<0.001). The CRM of birds had a linear effect (P<0.001) in trial 1, and a quadratic effect (P=0.001) in trial 2. The CRS and SS of broilers linearly increased, in trial 2 (P<0.001). In conclusion, increasing SID Arg:Lys ratios in diets reduced CP enhanced growth performance, skin quality and CR levels"																																												
in muscle and serum of broiler chickens from 01 to 21 and 22 to 44 days old.																																												
Keywords:  Essential  Amino  Acid.  Reduced  Crude  Protein  Content.  Broiler.  Skin																																												
Quality. Creatine Level.																																												
RESUMO																																												
"OLIVEIRA, Carlos Henrique de, M.Sc., Universidade Federal de Viçosa, agosto de"																																												
"2022. Diferentes relações arginina: lisina sobre o desempenho, a qualidade da pele, e os  níveis  de  creatina de frangos de corte alimentados com dietas reduzidas em proteína. Orientador: Luiz Fernando Teixeira Albino. Coorientador: Arele Arlindo Calderano."																																												
Foram conduzidos dois ensaios para avaliar os efeitos de diferentes relações arginina:																																												
"lisina digestível sobre o desempenho, a qualidade da pele, e os níveis de creatina no músculo e no sangue de frangos de corte alimentados com dietas reduzidas em proteína. Foram utilizados 1.540 frangos em cada experimento (1 a 21 dias e 22 a 44 dias de idade), onde foram distribuídos inteiramente ao acaso em 7 tratamentos, com 10 repetições com 22 animais. Uma dieta controle foi formulada para atender as exigências dos animais, e uma dieta com redução proteica foi formulada para atender as exigências dos animais, exceto para os níveis de arginina (Arg). As rações experimentais foram obtidas por adicionar seis níveis de L-Arginina à dieta reduzida em proteína, para atender seis relações de Arg: Lis dig. (94, 100, 106, 112, 118, e 124%). O peso corporal (PC), o ganho de peso médio (GP), o consumo médio de ração (CR), e a conversão alimentar (CA) foram avaliados de 01 a 21 dias, no ensaio 1, e de 22 a 44 dias, no ensaio 2. Aos 21 e aos 44 dias de idade, as aves foram abatidas para avaliar a espessura de pele (EP), a força da pele (FP), e os níveis de creatina no músculo (CM) e no sangue (CS). Os dados foram submetidos à ANOVA, ao nível de 5%, e os tratamentos foram individualmente contrastados ao controle pelo Teste Dunnett (P≤0.05). Análises de regressão foram realizados para modelar as variáveis avaliadas com as relações de Arg: Lis dig. O CR das aves não foi influenciado pelas diferentes relações de Arg: Lis dig. (P:0,05), enquanto o PC, o GP e a EP aumentaram linearmente em ambos os ensaios (P<0,001). A CA das aves melhorou linearmente nos ensaios 1 (P = 0,038) e 2 (P<0,001), enquanto o CM aumentou linearmente no ensaio 1 (P<0,001), e apresentou efeito quadrático no ensaio 2 (P=0,001). O CS das aves aumentou linearmente no ensaio 2 (P<0,001). O aumento das relações de arginina: lisina digestível em dietas reduzidas em proteína melhora o desempenho, a qualidade da pele, e as concentrações musculares de"																																												
séricas de creatina de frangos de corte de 01 a 21 e 22 a 44 dias de idade.																																												
Palavras-Chave: Aminoácidos Essenciais. Dietas Reduzidas Em Proteína. Frangos																																												
De Corte. Qualidade Da Pele. Níveis De Creatina.																																												
LIST OF TABLES																																												
Table 1. Control and reduced CP diets formulations in trial 1 from 01 to 21 days old.																																												
................................................................................................................................. 29																																												
Table 2. Control and reduced CP diets formulations in trial 2 from 22 to 44 days old.																																												
................................................................................................................................. 30																																												
"Table 3. Means of average daily feed intake (ADFI), body weight (BW), body weight"																																												
gain (BWG) and feed conversion ratio (FCR) of broilers fed diets with different SID Arg:Lys ratios and control diets in trials 1 and 2                                                         31																																												
Table 4. Means of creatine levels in muscle (CRM) and serum (CRS) of samples of																																												
breast and blood collected from broilers at 21 and 44 days old that were fed diets  with different SID Arg:Lys ratios and control diets in trials 1 and 2                            32																																												
Table 5. Means of skin thickness (ST) and skin strength (SS) of skin samples																																												
collected from broilers at 21 and 44 days old and were fed diets with different SID Arg:Lys ratios and control diets in trials 1 and 2                                                         33																																												
SUMMARY																																												
"DIFFERENT RATIOS OF ARGININE: LYSINE ON PERFORMANCE, SKIN QUALITY"																																												
AND  CREATINE  LEVELS  OF  BROILER  CHICKENS  FED  DIETS  REDUCED  IN PROTEIN CONTENT                                                                                                 11																																												
1. INTRODUCTION                                                                                                    12																																												
2. MATERIALS AND METHODS                                                                               15																																												
2.1 Ethics Committee                                                                                             15																																												
2.2 Common Procedures and Experimental Design                                              15																																												
2.3 Experimental Diets                                                                                           15																																												
2.4 Broiler Performance                                                                                         16																																												
2.5 Skin Quality                                                                                                      16																																												
2.6 Creatine Assays                                                                                               16																																												
2.7 Statistical Analysis                                                                                           17																																												
3. RESULTS                                                                                                               18																																												
4. DISCUSSION                                                                                                         20																																												
5. CONCLUSION                                                                                                       24																																												
REFERENCES                                                                                                           25																																												
"DIFFERENT RATIOS OF ARGININE: LYSINE ON PERFORMANCE, SKIN"																																												
QUALITY AND CREATINE LEVELS OF BROILER CHICKENS FED DIETS REDUCED IN PROTEIN CONTENT																																												
"Carlos H. Oliveiraa, Kelly M. M. Diasa, Romário D. Bernardesa, Thiago F. Dianaa,"																																												
"Ramalho J. B. Rodrigueirob, Arele A. Calderanoa, Luiz F. T. Albinoa."																																												
"aDepartment of Animal Science, Universidade Federal de Viçosa, 36570-900, Viçosa"																																												
"- MG, Brazil."																																												
"bCJ Corporation, Av. Engenheiro Luís Carlos Berrini, 04571-010, São Paulo – SP,"																																												
Brazil.																																												
"Published at Poultry Science, 2022, 102148"																																												
Paper history:																																												
"Initial Date Submitted May 30, 2022; Received in revised form August 04, 2022;"																																												
"Accepted August 19, 2022; Available online 27 August 2022. doi: https://doi.org/10.1016/j.psj.2022.102148."																																												
1. INTRODUCTION																																												
"For many years, diets have been formulated to meet broiler requirements according to"																																												
"crude protein (CP) content, which may result in some amino acid (AA) levels above the recommended levels. Consequently, there is considerable interest in the successful development of reduced CP diets associated with feeding costs and decreased nitrogen excretion and environmental pollution (Maia et al., 2021). The inclusion of unbound AAs (crystalline or synthetic) enables a substantial reduction in the protein levels, in which low-protein diets plus unbound AAs are formulated to meet the requirements for all AAs and are expressed as a percentage of lysine, the reference AA (Emment and Baker, 1997). However, tangible reductions in dietary CP can compromise broiler performance even if unbound AAs are supplemented to meet bird requirements, and the ratio of AAs to Lys is not permanent, as it is influenced by various factors such as amino acid antagonism (Chrystal et al., 2020)."																																												
"Conventionally, AA requirements for broiler chickens have been focused on its primarily functions as a structure in the protein chain. However, recent studies have shown that some AAs play important roles in multiple signaling pathways, thereby regulating gene expression, intracellular protein turnover, nutrient metabolism, immunology, and oxidative defense (Wu, 2010; Yu et al., 2022). Among the functional AAs, Arg is one of the most versatile in animal physiology because it is a precursor of several molecules, such as creatine, ornithine, nitric oxide, citrulline, proline and polyamines (Fernandes and Murakami, 2010; Birmani et al., 2019)."																																												
"Creatine (CR), as a precursor of phosphocreatine (PCR), has a direct role in protein accretion by improving the availability of adenosine triphosphate (ATP) for myosin (Portocarero and Braun, 2021). The CR: PCR system acts to transfer high-energy phosphate groups from the mitochondrial matrix to the sites of ATP utilization in the cytosol, acting as a reservoir of phosphate that can restore ATP from adenosine diphosphate (ADP) (Bender, 2012). Regeneration of ATP is particularly important in fast-growing species such as broiler chickens (Portocarero and Braun, 2021). The biosynthesis of CR is thoroughly understood and requires three AAs, Arg, Gly and Met, and two enzymes, L-arginine-glycine amidinotransferase (AGAT) and guanidinoacetate methyltransferase. Literature regarding broiler chicken responses to"																																												
dietary Arg levels reported that CR levels in muscle are directly affected by this AA.																																												
"Thus, the CR level in muscle can be used as a criterion to assess the Arg requirement"																																												
"of birds (Chamruspollert et al., 2002)."																																												
"Fragile skins can downgrade chicken carcass. Therefore, increases in skin strength are an important economic factor in poultry processing (Kafri et al., 1985). Christensen et al. (1995) reported an improvement in skin strength of female broilers as synthetic L-proline was incorporated into diets. Pro, Gly and hydroxyproline (Hyp) are the main components of collagen type I, a protein that confers strength and flexibility to skin, bones, and tendons, in addition to contributing to wound healing of those tissues (Aykın-Dinçer et al., 2017). A study carried out by Austic (1973) indicated that chicks fed a Pro-free diet converted approximately 7% of the dietary Arg to Pro. Therefore, Arg may contribute to improving the skin quality of broilers."																																												
"Arg plays an important role in broiler growth performance, participating in protein synthesis either directly as a monomer in the protein chain or indirectly as taking part in multiple metabolic pathways (Yao et al., 2008; Fernandes and Murakami, 2010). There is evidence that Arg is a powerful secretagogue that stimulates the release of growth hormone (GH) and insulin-like growth factor 1 (IGF-1) in the bloodstream (Silva et al., 2012). Furthermore, Arg acts as a trigger of target of rapamycin (TOR) signaling pathway activation, a complex that controls many aspects of cellular physiology, increasing protein synthesis and decreasing protein degradation (Dann and Thomas, 2006; Yao et al., 2008)."																																												
"Birds do not synthetize Arg efficiently due to the absence of a functional urea cycle, as the excretion of nitrogenous compounds by the uric acid pathway is not Arg-dependent (Bender, 2012). Therefore, Arg is an essential AA and must be supplied by nutritional programs to meet chicken physiological requirements. However, an excessive dietary Arg level could result in a negative effect on broiler physiology due to the antagonism between Arg and Lys, which may reduce food consumption, weight gain and Arg utilization in animal metabolism (Fernandes and Murakami, 2010). The mechanism behind the lysine-arginine antagonism has not been cleanly defined but it does appear to be linked to the reduced capacity for the renal tubes to reabsorb arginine, and reduced arginase activity (Maynard and Kidd, 2022)."																																												
"Owing to the struggle to determine the Arg:Lys ratio, especially in reduced CP diets due to Arg versatility in bird metabolism and its antagonism with Lys, we carried out the current research to assess the effects of arginine supplementation through different"																																												
"ratios of standardized ileal digestible (SID) Arg: Lys on the performance, CR levels in"																																												
"muscle and serum, and skin quality of broilers fed diets formulated with a reduction in"																																												
CP content.																																												
2. MATERIALS AND METHODS																																												
2.1 Ethics Committee																																												
All procedures adopted in this research were previously approved by the Ethics																																												
Committee in the Use of Farming Animals at the Federal University of Viçosa (CEUAP-																																												
"UFV) under protocol 01/2021, in accordance with the norms of the National Council for Experimentation Animal Control (CONCEA, 2008)."																																												
2.2 Common Procedures and Experimental Design																																												
The current research was divided into two dose–response trials according to the																																												
"growth phases of the animals: trial 1 (1 to 21 days of age) and trial 2 (22 to 44 days of age). The trials were performed at the Research & Extension Sector for Poultry Production and Nutrition from the Animal Science Department - Center for Agricultural Sciences, Federal University of Viçosa, State of Minas Gerais, Brazil."																																												
"In both  trials, Cobb500™ male broiler chicks (Cobb-Vantress, Inc., East Siloam Springs, Arkansas, USA) were obtained from a commercial hatchery at 1 day old, where all chicks received vaccinations for Marek’s disease, Newcastle disease, and infectious bronchitis. Broiler chicks were reared into floor pens equipped with one tubular feeder of 20 kg, five in-line nipple drinkers, and a litter system of fresh wood shavings. Experimental diets and water were provided ad libitum throughout the experimental period. Temperature and light programs were set according to genetic guidelines."																																												
"A total of 1,540 chickens with initial body weights of 37.25 ± 2.4 g in trial 1 and 958.62"																																												
"± 61.8 g in trial 2 were distributed in a completely randomized design in 7 treatments, with 10 replicates with 22 birds each. In trial 2, prior to achieving 22 d, broiler chicks were reared in solid wall houses, equipped with cross ventilation type and stocking density of 38kg/m2, according to conditions established by Cobb500™ guideline"																																												
recommendations and fed with diets formulated according to Rostagno et al. (2017).																																												
2.3 Experimental Diets																																												
The experimental diets were based on corn and soybean meal. A control diet was																																												
"formulated to cover all nutrient recommendations according to Rostagno et al. (2017),"																																												
meeting the ratios of SID Arg: Lys of 107% and CP of 23.11% in trial 1 and 20.77% in																																												
trial 2 (Table 1 and 2).																																												
"A CP reduced diet was formulated to meet the nutritional recommendations for broilers, except for the SID Arg level, with 21.38% and 19.04% of CP, in trial 1 and 2, respectively. To reduce protein content, SID Arg and SID Lys were less supplied, in which the SID Arg:Lys ratio was decreased to 94%, in both trials (Table 1 and 2). L- arginine (CJ Corporation, Jung-gu, Seoul, South Korea) was added to CP reduced diet at six different levels in trial 1 (0, 0.07, 0.14, 0.21, 0.28 and 0.35%) and trial 2 (0, 0.06,"																																												
"0.12, 0.18, 0.24 and 0.30%) to meet the SID Arg:Lys ratios of 94, 100, 106, 112, 118"																																												
and 124%. (Table 1 and 2).																																												
2.4 Broiler Performance																																												
Broiler chickens and experimental diets were individually weighed at days 1 and 21 in																																												
trial 1 and at Days 22 and 44 in trial 2 for performance evaluation (body weight – BW; body weight gain – BWG; average daily feed intake – ADFI; and feed conversion ratio																																												
"- FCR). In the case of broiler mortality, the corpse was removed, and the leftover feed"																																												
was weighed to correct the ADFI.																																												
2.5 Skin Quality																																												
Three birds per replicate were slaughtered by cervical dislocation at 21 days old in trial																																												
"1 and at 44 days old in trial 2. The carcass was defeathered (dry, handpicked) to remove skin samples (5 x 5 cm) from the lateral region of the left and right pelvic back, according to the methodology proposed by Bilgili et al. (1993). The skin samples were evaluated using a micrometer to measure skin thickness (ST) and a texturometer (Warner–Bratzler® 2000, G-R Electric Company, Manhattan, KS, USA) to measure skin strength (SS). The latter mechanism consisted of passing a blade over the skin,"																																												
measuring the strength needed to cut off the material.																																												
2.6 Creatine Assays																																												
An internal portion of the Pectoralis profundus (Sasami) muscle was collected from the																																												
"carcass. Sasami are the slender muscles which can be found on either side of the breastbone, beneath the large breast muscle. Creatine levels in muscle (CRM) were assayed using an EnzyChrom Creatine Assay Kit (ECRT-100, BioAssay Systems"																																												
"Corporate, Hayward, California, USA) according to the manufacturer’s protocol. In the"																																												
"laboratory analysis, 0.100 g of muscle samples was homogenized in 1 mL of distilled"																																												
"water and centrifuged at 1000 rpm for 10 minutes. The supernatant was collected and mixed with a creatine assay kit in a 96-well plate. Creatine concentrations in solution were read at OD570nm using a spectrophotometer (Multiskan TM Go, Thermo Fisher Scientific Inc., Waltham, Massachusetts, USA). The creatine standard range of the assay was 0 to 1 μM. The data were converted to ppm by a conversion factor of 0.131 according to the manufacturer’s protocol."																																												
"Blood samples were collected from birds at 44 days old only in trial 2 to assess the creatine levels in serum (CRS). The blood samples were collected after a fasting period of 12 hours by the chickens, placed in CAT Serum Activator Coagulation vacuum tubes and sent immediately to an analysis laboratory (ViçosaLab, Viçosa, Minas Gerais,"																																												
"Brazil) for CRS quantification, in μmol/L."																																												
2.7 Statistical Analysis																																												
Data were analyzed by one-way ANOVA using ExpDes.pt from the R statistical																																												
"package (R Software v.4.0.4). Dunnett's test (P≤0.05) was used to compare each variable from treatments with diets reduced in CP to the control group. Additionally, linear and quadratic regressions were performed to model and analyze the relationships between the variables assessed and the ratios of SID Arg: Lys. When quadratic responses were detected, the optimal SID Arg:Lys ratio was calculated by taking the first derivative of the quadratic equation and subsequently estimating 95% of  the  maximum  responses.  The  control  treatment  was  not  considered  in  the"																																												
regression analysis.																																												
3. RESULTS																																												
The SID Arg:Lys ratios in diets reduced in CP did not affect the ADFI of broiler chickens																																												
in trial 1 (P = 0.394) and trial 2 (P = 0.702) (Table 3). There were no differences between the treatments and the control group in the ADFI of broilers in either trial (P>0.05) (Table 3).																																												
"The increasing ratios of SID Arg: Lys in diets reduced in CP linearly increased the BW and BWG of birds in trials 1 and 2 (P<0.001) (Table 3). Furthermore, the FCRs of broilers linearly decreased with increasing ratios of SID Arg: Lys in diets and were reduced in CP content in trial 1 (P = 0.038) and trial 2 (P<0.001) (Table 3)."																																												
"By comparing each SID Arg:Lys ratio in diets reduced in CP with the control group (Table 3), the BW and BWG of birds were lower (P≤0.05) in the treatments with diets meeting the ratios of 94, 100, and 106% SID Arg: Lys, whereas it did not differ (P>0.05) in diets meeting the ratios of 112, 118, and 124%, in trial 1. Additionally, the FCR of birds was worse than the ones from control (P≤0.05) when were fed diets with 94% of SID Arg:Lys ratio, and it did not differ in the others SID Arg:Lys ratios (100, 106, 112, 118, and 124%) (P>0.05)."																																												
"In trial 2, only the diets with 94 and 100% of SID Arg:Lys ratio showed lower BW and BWG (P≤0.05), whereas the ratios of 106, 112, 118, and 124% shower similar results than control group (P>0.05) (Table 3). Furthermore, when birds were fed diets with 94, 100, and 106% of SID Arg:Lys ratio, the FCR was worse than the ones from control group (P≤0.05), whereas the birds fed diets with 112, 118, and 124% SID Arg:Lys showed similar FCR (P>0.05) (Table 3)."																																												
"The increasing ratios from 94 to 124% of SID Arg: Lys linearly increased the CRM of broilers in trial 1 (P<0.001) (Table 4). However, there was a quadratic effect on the CRM of broilers within the SID Arg:Lys ratios in trial 2 (P = 0.001), with an optimization point at the estimated level of 112% SID Arg: Lys (Table 4)."																																												
"The contrast between the treatments with reduced CP and the control group showed that in trial 1, birds fed diets until the ratio of 112% SID Arg: Lys showed lower CRM than birds from the control group (P≤0.05), whereas birds fed a diet meeting the ratio of 124% SID Arg: Lys showed higher CRM (P<0.05) (Table 4). In trial 2, only the chickens fed diets meeting SID Arg:Lys ratios of 112 and 118% showed higher CRM"																																												
than the chickens from the control group (P≤0.05) (Table 4).																																												
The CRS of broilers at 44 days old showed a linear increase as the ratio of SID Arg:																																												
Lys increased in diets reduced in CP content (P<0.001) (Table 4). There were no differences in CRS between birds from the treatment and control groups (P>0.05).																																												
The ST of broilers linearly increased in trials 1 and 2 (P<0.001) when the ratios of SID Arg: Lys increased from 94 to 124% in diets reduced in CP content (Table 5).																																												
"By contrasting the birds from treatments with reduced CP and those from the control group, in trial 1, the ST was lower (P≤0.05) in the SID Arg:Lys ratios of 94 and 100%, it was similar (P>0.05) in the ratio of 106%, and it was higher (P≤0.05) in the ratios of 112, 118, and 124% (Table 5). In trial 2, diets with ratios of 94 and 100% showed lower ST than control group (P≤0.05), whereas diets with 106 and 112 showed similar ST (P>0.05), and diets with 118 and 124% shower higher ST (P≤0.05) (Table 5)."																																												
"The SID Arg:Lys ratios did not influence the SS of broilers in trial 1 (P = 0.108) (Table 5). However, the SS linearly increased as the increasing ratios of SID Arg: Lys in diets decreased in CP in trial 2 (P<0.001) (Table 5). When comparing the treatments to the control group, the SS of broilers were lower when they were fed diets meeting the ratios"																																												
"of 94, 100, 106 and 112% SID Arg: Lys (P≤0.05) in trial 2 (Table 5)."																																												
4. DISCUSSION																																												
Chickens fed diets reduced in CP content would not be expected to be AA-deficient for																																												
"meeting all essential AA requirements, according to Rostagno et al. (2017), except for Arg. Therefore, the effects of treatments on broiler performance should be attributed to different SID Arg:Lys ratios. Rostagno et al. (2017) recommended a ratio of 107% SID Arg: Lys in broiler diets. However, our findings demonstrated that when there was a reduction in CP of diets, broiler performance linearly improved as the ratio of SID Arg: Lys increased, with the highest ratio of 124% showing the best results for BW, BWG and FCR. Therefore, L-arginine supplementation seems to enhance chicken performance in Arg-deficient diets. Such outcomes support previous research findings that L-arginine supplementation in Arg-deficient diets leads to an increase in BW and, consequently, BWG of broiler chickens (Yu et al., 2018; Xu et al., 2018; Castro et al., 2019). However, the authors reported that Arg-excessive diets had a nonpositive effect on the growth performance of animals by decreasing BW and BWG. We did not notice a detrimental ratio of SID Arg: Lys in diets reduced in CP, which indicates that the SID Arg in diets was not overly supplied, even at the highest SID Arg:Lys ratio (124%)."																																												
"There are multiple ways by which Arg acts on the growth performance of broiler chickens: it acts as a monometer in the protein chain, stimulates anabolic hormone release, and activates the TOR signaling pathway. Tsugawa et al. (2019) conducted mouse experiments to analyze the mechanism regulating arginine-induced IGF-1 secretion. Although the mechanism has not been fully elucidated, Arg seems to induce IGF-1 secretion by either inducing GH secretion and consequently stimulating IGF-1 translation and secretion or releasing IGF-1 retention in the endoplasmic reticulum. Furthermore, Yu et al. (2018) reported an increase in IGF-1 levels in the serum of broilers at 42 days old as the dietary arginine level increased. The GH/IGF axis is a key mechanism for skeletal muscle hypertrophy due to its involvement in numerous anabolic and catabolic events (Frost and Lang, 2012)."																																												
"Target of rapamycin (TOR) signaling pathway activation consists of a phosphorylation cascade, especially the phosphorylation of TOR, ribosomal protein S6 kinase (S6K1), and eukaryotic initiation factor (eIF)-4E-binding protein-1 (4E-BP1), which activate the eIF4F complex, mediating the binding of mRNA to the ribosomal complex (Yonezawa et al., 2004). Yuan et al. (2015) reported that the mRNA abundance levels of TOR, 4E-"																																												
BP1 and S6K1 increased as the extracellular concentrations of L-Arg increased in																																												
"embryo chicken cells cultured in vitro. Similarly, Yuan et al. (2016) concluded that"																																												
"increasing the dietary level of L-Arg increased the liver fractional protein synthesis rate and fractional protein gain rate of laying hens by upregulating the gene expression of the TOR signaling pathway. Therefore, in our study, the growth performance results may be attributed to the role of Arg in protein synthesis contributing to protein structure, as well as via IGF-1 and TOR pathway activation."																																												
"Contrasting the treatments with diets reduced in CP with the control diet, we noticed that the BW and BWG of birds did not differ from the ratios of 112 and 106% of SID Arg: Lys, in trial 1 and 2, respectively. However, these diets with reduced CP supplied less SID Arg and SID Lys than control diet, which indicates that the control diet could have been formulated with excess of those AAs."																																												
"Arg supplementation has been shown to be effective in CR maintenance in broilers fed Arg-deficient diets, as Arg is a precursor of CR and cannot be synthesized efficiently by birds (Chamruspollert et al., 2002). Our findings showed that increasing the ratios of SID Arg: Lys in diets reduced CP and increased CRM. These results are supported by DeGroot et al. (2018), who demonstrated that an Arg-deficient basal diet containing 0.84% SID Arg was detrimental to the growth performance of broilers by producing disruptions to CR and PCR levels in muscle. However, when the authors supplied 0.16 and 0.32% L-arginine to this Arg-deficient diet, CR and PCR levels in muscle proportionally increased."																																												
"In the present study, the CRM of broilers was affected in different ways between both trials, where the increase in SID Arg:Lys ratios in diets reduced in CP linearly increased the CRM of chickens in trial 1 and quadratically increased the CRM of birds in trial 2. These results can be explained by the difference in CR requirements of broilers during their growth. The current lineages of broiler chickens are the result of successful genetic selection programs to achieve rapid growth, improvements in body conformation, and a consequent reduction in animal slaughter age (Zuidhof, 2014). Consequently, the nutritional requirements are higher in the starter phase than in the finisher phase. Thus, the highest ratio of 124% SID Arg: Lys in trial 1 (from 1 to 21 days old) was beneficial to the CRM of birds since the CR demand was being met. Conversely, the highest ratio of 124% SID Arg: Lys in trial 2 (from 22 to 44 days old) was detrimental to the CRM of broilers, which indicates that Arg was overly supplied, exceeding CR demands and downregulating CR synthesis. This hypothesis was"																																												
"confirmed by Hasegawa et al. (2017), who reported a decrease in hepatic AGAT"																																												
activities as the dietary Arg levels increased from deficient to excessive. AGAT is the																																												
"principal regulatory site and rate-limiting step in the biosynthesis of CR. Thus, when Arg was deficient in diets, it became the limiting AA for CR synthesis, increasing the AGAT activity to meet CR demands. Once the Arg dietary level was increased to exceed the CR requirements of broilers, AGAT activities decreased through a downregulatory mechanism."																																												
"Analyzing the contrast between the treatments with diets reduced in CP and the control group, in trial 1, we found that broilers fed diets with ratios lower than 118% of SID Arg: Lys showed lower CRM than birds from the control group, whereas the ones fed diets with the highest ratio of 124% SID Arg: Lys showed higher CRM. Interestingly, the ratio of 118% SID Arg: Lys in the diet was reduced in CP-supplemented 1.357% SID Arg, similar to the control diet, which supplied 1.344% SID Arg, whereas the ratio of 124% SID Arg: Lys in the diet was reduced in CP-supplemented 1.426% SID Arg. Thus, the increase in SID Arg levels seems to increase the CRM of broilers from 01 to 21 days old."																																												
"In trial 2, only the ratios of 112 and 118% SID Arg: Lys showed higher CRM than control group. The ratios of 112 and 118% SID Arg: Lys supplied 1.12 and 1.18% of SID Arg, respectively, whereas the control diet supplied 1.203% of SID Arg. Therefore, levels above 1.18% of SID Arg could be in excess, decreasing the CRM through a downregulatory mechanism in CR synthesis."																																												
"In the present study, the CRS of birds also increased as the SID Arg:Lys ratio increased. Such results are supported by DeGroot et al. (2018), who observed an increase in CRS as the Arg dietary levels increased from 0.84 to 1.16% of SID Arg. Such outcomes are supported by the fact that the pathway of CR synthesis occurs primarily in the liver and kidneys, which is released into the bloodstream and then taken up by muscle fibers by a CR transporter (Bender, 2012). Thus, an increase in dietary Arg may result in an increase in CR biosynthesis and, consequently, an increase in CR released into the bloodstream."																																												
"The participation of Arg in skin quality improvement has not been fully elucidated since there are many contradictory results about the role of Arg in Pro biosynthesis. Recently, studies have shown that, in contrast to mammals, the synthesis of Pro from Arg in birds is limited because of low arginase activity in their tissues. Arginase hydrolyzes Arg to ornithine  (Orn),  and  the  latter  is  converted  to  Pro  by  the  enzyme  ornithine-"																																												
"aminotransferase (OAT) (Wu, 2018; He et al., 2021). However, Furakawa et al. (2021)"																																												
carried out a study to investigate the synthesis of polyamines from Arg and Pro in																																												
"chickens and reported that mitochondrial arginase located in bird kidneys can hydrolyze Arg into Orn. These findings support previous research that indicated the presence of key enzymes responsible for Pro biosynthesis from Arg in the liver and kidneys of chickens, i.e., arginase, OAT, and pyrroline-5-carboxylic acid (P5C) reductase (Vecchio and Kalman, 1968; Austic and Nesheim, 1971). Additionally, Klain and Johnson (1962) demonstrated that administration of labeled arginine-C14 injections in chickens resulted in the labeling of Pro in the liver, which indicates a direct conversion of Arg to Pro. As Pro is an important structure of collagen, the possible influence between Arg dietary levels and Pro biosynthesis may explain our results of improvements in skin quality throughout the increase in SID Arg:Lys ratios. However, more studies should be conducted to elucidate the physiological mechanism involved"																																												
in the effects of Arg on broiler skins.																																												
5. CONCLUSION																																												
The results obtained in trial 1 demonstrate that increasing ratios of SID Arg: Lys from																																												
"94 to 124% in diets reduced in protein content linearly enhances the growth performance, creatine level in muscle and skin quality of broiler chickens from 01 to 21 days old, in which the recommended ratio is 124% of SID Arg: Lys to show better results in BW, BWG, FCR, CRM and ST. The results obtained in trial 2 demonstrate that although the creatine level in muscle has a quadratic effect within the ratios of SID Arg: Lys in diets reduced in CP, the majority of variables assessed linearly increase as the ratios of SID Arg: Lys increase from 94 to 124%, in which the recommended ratio is 124% of SID Arg:Lys to show better results in BW, BWG, FCR, CRS ST and SS of broiler chickens from 22 to 44 days old. More studies must be carried out to better understand  the  mechanisms  of  Arg  on  creatine  downregulation  and  proline"																																												
biosynthesis.																																												
REFERENCES																																												
"ALE SAHEB, F. S. S.; AZARFAR, A.; GHEISARI, A.; KHOSRAVINIA, H. Performance"																																												
"and physiological responses of broiler chickens to supplemental guanidinoacetic acid in arginine-deficient diets. British Poultry Science, v. 60, n. 2, p. 161-168, 2019."																																												
"AUSTIC, R.E. Conversion of arginine to proline in the chick. The Journal of Nutrition,"																																												
"v. 103, n. 7, p. 999-1007, 1973."																																												
"AYKIN-DINÇER,   E.;   KOC,   A.;   ERBAS,   M.   Extraction   and   physicochemical"																																												
"characterization  of  broiler  (Gallus  gallus  domesticus)  skin  gelatin  compared  to commercial bovine gelatin. Poultry Science, v. 96, n. 11, p. 4124-4131, 2017."																																												
"BENDER,  D.  A.  Amino  Acids  Synthesized  from  Glutamate:  Glutamine,  Proline,"																																												
"Ornithine, Citrulline and Arginine. In: Amino Acid Metabolism. 3rd ed. Chichester, West Sussex, UK: Wiley-Blackwell, 2012. p. 157-223."																																												
"BILGILI, S. F.; ECKMAN, M. K.; BUSHONG, R. D. Broiler Skin Strength: Influence of"																																												
"Age, Sex, and Feathering Rate. Journal of Applied Poultry Research, v. 2, n. 2, p. 135-141, 1993."																																												
"BIRMANI, W.; RAZA, A.; NAWAB, A.; TANG, S.; GHANI, M.; LI, G.; XIAO, M.; AN, L."																																												
"Importance of arginine as immune regulator in animal nutrition. International Journal of Veterinary Science, v. 5, n. 1, p. 1-10, 2019."																																												
"BROSNAN, J. T.; WIJEKOON, E. P.; WARFORD-WOOLGAR, L; TROTTIER, N. L.;"																																												
"BROSNAN, M. E.; BRUNTON, J. A.; BERTOLO, R. F. Creatine Synthesis Is a Major Metabolic Process in Neonatal Piglets and Has Important Implications for Amino Acid Metabolism and Methyl Balance. The Journal of Nutrition, v. 139, n. 7, p. 1292-1297, 2009."																																												
"CASTRO, F. L.; SU, S.; CHOI, H.; KOO, E.; KIM, W. K. L-Arginine supplementation"																																												
"enhances growth performance, lean muscle, and bone density but not fat in broiler chickens. Poultry Science, v. 98, n. 4, p. 1716-1722, 2019."																																												
"CHAMRUSPOLLERT, M.; PESTI, G. M.; BAKALLI, R. I. Dietary Interrelationships"																																												
"among Arginine, Methionine, and Lysine in Young Broiler Chicks. British Journal of Nutrition, v. 88, n. 6, p. 655-660, 2002."																																												
"CHRISTENSEN K. D.; ZIMMERMANN, N. G.; WYATT, C. L.; GOODMAN, T. N.;"																																												
"BUHR, R. J.; TWINING, P. F. Mitigating the effects of halofuginone on skin strength by feeding L-proline to broiler chickens. Poultry Science, v. 74, n. 10, p. 1610-1621, 1995."																																												
"CHRYSTAL, P. V.; MOSS, A. F.; KHODDAMI, A.; NARANJO, V. D.; SELLE, P. H.;"																																												
"LIU, S. Y. Effects of reduced crude protein levels, dietary electrolyte balance, and energy density on the performance of broiler chickens offered maize-based diets with evaluations of starch, protein, and amino acid metabolism. Poultry Science, v. 99, n. 3, p. 1421-1431, 2020."																																												
"DANN, S. G.; THOMAS, G. The amino acid sensitive TOR pathway from yeast to"																																												
"mammals. FEBS letters, v. 580, n. 12, p. 2821-2829, 2006."																																												
"DEGROOT, A. A.; BRAUN, U.; DILGER, R. N. Efficacy of guanidinoacetic acid on"																																												
"growth and muscle energy metabolism in broiler chicks receiving arginine-deficient diets. Poultry Science, v. 97, n. 3, p. 890-900, 2018."																																												
"EMMERT, J.; BAKER, D. Use of the Ideal Protein Concept for Precision Formulation"																																												
"of Amino Acid Levels in Broiler Diets. Journal of Applied Poultry Research, v. 6, p. 462-470, 1997."																																												
"ESSER,  A.  F.;  GONÇALVES,  D.  R.;  RORIG,  A.;  CRISTO,  A.  B.;  PERINI,  R.;"																																												
"FERNANDES, J. I. Effects of Guanidinoacetic Acid and Arginine Supplementation to Vegetable Diets Fed to Broiler Chickens Subjected to Heat Stress before Slaughter. Revista Brasileira de Ciência Avícola, v. 19, n. 3, p. 429-436, 2017."																																												
"FERNANDES, J.; MURAKAMI, A. Arginine Metabolism in Uricotelic Species. Acta"																																												
"Scientiarum. Health Sciences, v. 32, p. 10990, 2010."																																												
"FROST, R.  A.; LANG,  C. H.  Multifaceted  role  of  insulin-like  growth  factors  and"																																												
"mammalian target of rapamycin in skeletal muscle. Endocrinology & Metabolism Clinics of North America, v. 41, n.  2, p. 297-322, 2012."																																												
"FURUKAWA, K.; HE, W.; BAILEY, C. A.; BAZER, F. W.; TOYOMIZU, M.; WU. G."																																												
Polyamine synthesis from arginine and proline in tissues of developing chickens.																																												
"Amino Acids, v. 53, p. 1739-1748, 2021."																																												
"HASEGAWA, E.; SHIRAISHI, J. I.; OHTA, Y. Effects of Dietary Methionine or Arginine"																																												
"Levels on the Urinary Creatinine Excretion in Broiler Chicks. Poultry Science, v. 4, n. 2, p. 167-172, 2017."																																												
"HE, W.; LI, P.; WU, G. Amino Acid Nutrition and Metabolism in Chickens. Advances"																																												
"in Experimental Medicine and Biology, v. 1285, p. 109-131, 2021."																																												
"KAFRI I.; CHERRY, J. A.; JONES, D. E.; SIEGEL, P. B. Breaking strength and"																																												
composition of the skin of broiler chicks: response to dietary calorie-protein ratios.																																												
"Poultry Science, v. 64, n. 11, p. 2143-2149, 1985."																																												
"KLAIN,  G.;  JOHNSON,  B.  C.  Metabolism  of  labeled  aminoethanol,  glycine,  and"																																												
"arginine in the chick. Journal of Biological Chemistry, v. 237, p. 123-126, 1962."																																												
"MAIA, R.; ALBINO, L. F.; ROSTAGNO, H. S.; JUNIOR, M.; KREUZ, B.; SILVA, R.;"																																												
"FARIA, B.; CALDERANO A. Low crude protein diets for broiler chickens aged 8 to 21 days should have a 50% essential-to-total nitrogen ratio. Animal Feed Science and Technology, v. 271, p. 114709, 2021."																																												
"MAYNARD, C. W.; KIDD, M. T. Broiler Amino Acid Research: Then and Now. In:"																																												
"TÉLLEZ, G.; LATORRE, J. D.; MARTÍNEZ-AGUILAR, P. Y. Broiler Industry. London:"																																												
"Intech Open, 2022."																																												
"NESHEIM, M.C. Arginine, ornithine and proline metabolism of chicks: influence of diet"																																												
"and heredity. The Journal of Nutrition, v. 101, n. 10, p. 1403-1413, 1971."																																												
"OH, H. S.; OH, S. K.; LEE, J. S. Effects of L-arginine on growth hormone and insulin-"																																												
"like growth factor 1. Food Science and Biotechnology, v. 26, p. 1749-1754, 2017."																																												
"PORTOCARERO, N.; BRAUN, U. The physiological role of guanidinoacetic acid and"																																												
"its relationship with arginine in broiler chickens. Poultry Science, v. 100, p. 101203, 2021."																																												
"ROSTAGNO, H. S.; ALBINO, L. F.; HANNAS, M. I.; DONZELE, J. L.; SAKOMURA, N."																																												
"K.; PERAZZO, F. G.; SARAIVA, A.; ABREU, M. L.; RODRIGUES, P. B.; OLIVEIRA, R."																																												
"F.; BARRETO, S. L; BRITO, C. O. Brazilian Tables for Poultry and Swine. Translated by Bettina Gertum Becker. 4th ed. Viçosa: Department of Animal Science, UFV, Viçosa, Minas Gerais, Brazil, 2017. 488p"																																												
"SILVA, L. M.; MURAKAMI, A. E.; FERNANDES, J. I.; DALLA ROSA, D.; URGNANI, J."																																												
"F. Effects of dietary arginine supplementation on broiler breeder egg production and hatchability. Brazilian Journal of Poultry Science, v. 14, n. 4, p. 267-273, 2012."																																												
"STUART, J. A.; PAGE, M. M. Plasma IGF-1 is negatively correlated with body mass in"																																												
"a comparison of 36 mammalian species. Mechanisms of Ageing and Development, v. 131, n. 9, p. 591-598, 2010."																																												
"TSUGAWA, Y.; HANDA, H.; IMAI, T. Arginine induces IGF-1 secretion from the"																																												
"endoplasmic reticulum. Biochemical and Biophysical Research Communications, v. 514, n. 4, p. 1128-1132, 2019."																																												
"WU,  G.;  BAZER,  F.  W.;  DAVIS,  T.  A.;  KIM,  S.  W.;  LI,  P.;  RHOADS,  J.  M.;"																																												
"SATTERFIELD, M. C.; SMITH, S. B.; SPENCER, T. E.; YIN, Y. Arginine metabolism"																																												
"and nutrition in growth, health, and disease. Amino Acids, v. 37, n. 1, p. 153-68, 2009."																																												
"WU, G. Functional Amino Acids in Growth, Reproduction, and Health. Advances in"																																												
"Nutrition, v. 1, p. 31–37, 2010."																																												
"WU, G. Functional Amino Acids in Nutrition and Health. Amino Acids, v. 45, n. 3, p."																																												
"407-411, 2013."																																												
"WU, G. Nutrition and Metabolism of Protein and Amino Acids. In: Principles of Animal"																																												
"Nutrition. Boca Raton, New York: Taylor & Francis, 2018. p. 349-448."																																												
"WU, Z.; HOU, Y; HU, S.; BAZER, F. W.; MEININGER, C. J.; MCNEAL, C. J.; WU G."																																												
"Catabolism and safety of supplemental L-arginine in animals. Amino Acids, v. 48, n. 7, p. 1541-1552, 2016."																																												
"XU,  Y.  Q.;  GUO,  Y. W.; SHI,  B. L.;  YAN,  S. M.; GUO,  X.  Y.  Dietary  arginine"																																												
"supplementation enhances the growth performance and immune status of broiler chickens. Livestock Science, v. 209, p. 8-13, 2018."																																												
"YAO, K.; YIN, Y.; CHU, W.; LIU, Z.; DENG, D.; LI, T.; HUANG, R.; ZHANG, J.; TAN,"																																												
"B.; WANG, W.; WU, G. Dietary Arginine Supplementation Increases mTOR Signaling Activity in Skeletal Muscle of Neonatal Pigs. The Journal of Nutrition, v. 138, n. 5, p. 867-872, 2008."																																												
"YU, J.; YANG, H.; WANG, Z.; DAI, H.; XU, L.; LING, C. Effects of arginine on the"																																												
"growth performance, hormones, digestive organ development and intestinal morphology in the early growth stage of layer chickens. Italian Journal of Animal Science, v. 17, n. 4, p. 1077-1082, 2018."																																												
"YU, H.; SUN, L.; FAN, W.; CHEN, H.; GUO, Y.; LIU, Y.; GAO, W.; ZHANG, W. MAI, K."																																												
"Effects of dietary arginine on growth, anti-oxidative enzymes, biomarkers of immunity, amino acid metabolism and resistance to Vibrio parahaemolyticus challenge in abalone Haliotis discus hannai. Aquaculture, v. 549, p. 8444-8486, 2022."																																												
"YUAN, C.; DING,  Y.; HE, Q.; AZZAM,  M. M.; LU, J. J.; ZOU, X. T. L-arginine"																																												
"upregulates the gene expression of target of rapamycin signaling pathway and stimulates protein synthesis in chicken intestinal epithelial cells. Poultry Science, v. 94, n. 5, p. 1043-1051, 2015."																																												
"YUAN, C.; BU, X. C.; YAN, H. X.; LU, J. J.; ZOU, X. T. Dietary L-arginine levels affect"																																												
"the liver protein turnover and alter the expression of genes related to protein synthesis and proteolysis of laying hens. Poultry Science, v. 95, n. 2, p. 261-267, 2016."																																												
"YONEZAWA,  K.;  YOSHINO,  K.  I.;  TOKUNAGA,  C.;  HARA,  K.  Kinase  activities"																																												
"associated with mTOR. Current Topics in Microbiology and Immunology, v. 279, p. 271-282, 2004."																																												
"ZUIDHOF, M. J.; SCHNEIDER, B. L.; CARNEY, V. L.; KORVER, D. R.; ROBINSON,"																																												
"F. E. Growth, efficiency, and yield of commercial broilers from 1957, 1978, and 2005."																																												
"Poultry Science, v. 93, p. 2970-2982, 2014."																																												
Table 1. Control and reduced CP diets formulations in trial 1 from 01 to 21 days old.																																												
Diet Reduced CP																																												
Ingredient (%)                              Control																																												
SID Arg:Lys ratio (%)																																												
																94					100			106			112				118					124								
Corn										"5,813"						"6,191"					"6,191"			"6,191"			"6,191"				"6,191"					"6,191"								
Soybean meal										"2,413"						"1,930"					"1,930"			"1,930"			"1,930"				"1,930"					"1,930"								
Corn gluten meal										600						600					600			600			600				600					600								
Fish meal										300						300					300			300			300				300					300								
Plasma										200						200					200			200			200				200					200								
Dicalcium phosphate										150						153					153			153			153				153					153								
Limestone										088						090					090			090			090				090					090								
Salt										013						013					013			013			013				013					013								
Soybean oil										276						190					190			190			190				190					190								
"L-Glutamic acid, 99%"										000						085					085			085			085				085					085								
"Choline chloride, 60%"										010						010					010			010			010				010					010								
Starch										000						040					033			026			019				012					005								
L-Lysine HCl										035						036					036			036			036				036					036								
L-Methionine										024						029					029			029			029				029					029								
Potassium carbonate										000						025					025			025			025				025					025								
Sodium bicarbonate										025						025					025			025			025				025					025								
"L-Glycine, 98,5%"										002						018					018			018			018				018					018								
"L-Threonine, 98,5%"										004						011					011			011			011				011					011								
"L-Isoleucine, 98,5%"										001						009					009			009			009				009					009								
"L-Valine, 96,5%"										000						009					009			009			009				009					009								
"L-Tryptophan, 98%"										000						003					003			003			003				003					003								
"L-Arginine, 98,5%"										013						000					007			014			021				028					035								
Mineral Premix1										013						013					013			013			013				013					013								
Vitamin Premix2										015						015					015			015			015				015					015								
"Salinomycin, 12%"										006						006					006			006			006				006					006								
BHT3										001						001					001			001			001				001					001								
Composition																																												
"Crude Protein, %"										"2,311"						"2,138"					"2,138"			"2,138"			"2,138"				"2,138"					"2,138"								
"Metabolizable energy, kcal/kg"										3.150						3.150					3.150			3.150			3.150				3.150					3.150								
"Calcium, %"										"0,970"						"0,970"					"0,970"			"0,970"			"0,970"				"0,970"					"0,970"								
"Phosphorus available, %"										"0,460"						"0,460"					"0,460"			"0,460"			"0,460"				"0,460"					"0,460"								
"SID Arginine, %"										"1,344"						"1,081"					"1,150"			"1,219"			"1,288"				"1,357"					"1,426"								
"SID Lysine, %"										"1,256"						"1,150"					"1,150"			"1,150"			"1,150"				"1,150"					"1,150"								
"1Trace mineral premix provided per kg of diet: Mn, 58.36 g; Fe, 41.68 g; Zn, 54.21 g; Cu,"																																												
"8.31 g; I, 0.84 g; Se, 0.25 g."																																												
"2Vitamin premix provided per kg of diet: vitamin A, 9,638,000 IU; vitamin D3, 2,410,000 IU; vitamin E, 36,100 IU; vitamin B1, 2.60 g; vitamin B2, 6.45 g; vitamin B6, 3.61 g; vitamin B12,"																																												
"15.9 mg; vitamin K3, 1.94 g; pantothenic acid, 12.95 g; nicotinic acid, 39.20 g; folic acid, 0.90 g; biotin, 89.80 mg."																																												
3Antioxidant Butylhydroxytoluene.																																												
Table 2. Control and reduced CP diets formulations in trial 2 from 22 to 44 days old.																																												
Diet Reduced CP																																												
Ingredient (%)							Control												SID Arg:Lys ratio (%)																									
														94					100				106		112					118					124									
Corn							"6,534"							"6,877"					"6,877"				"6,877"		"6,877"					"6,877"					"6,877"									
Soybean meal							"1,911"							"1,463"					"1,463"				"1,463"		"1,463"					"1,463"					"1,463"									
Corn gluten meal							500							500					500				500		500					500					500									
Fish meal							300							300					300				300		300					300					300									
Plasma							200							200					200				200		200					200					200									
Dicalcium phosphate							109							113					113				113		113					113					113									
Limestone							063							064					064				064		064					064					064									
Salt							010							010					010				010		010					010					010									
Soybean oil							230							152					152				152		152					152					152									
"L-Glutamic acid, 99%"							000							085					085				085		085					085					085									
"Choline chloride, 60%"							010							010					010				010		010					010					010									
Starch							000							040					034				028		022					016					010									
L-Lysine HCl							034							032					032				032		032					032					032									
L-Methionine							020							024					024				024		024					024					024									
Potassium carbonate							000							028					028				028		028					028					028									
Sodium bicarbonate							025							025					025				025		025					025					025									
"L-Glycine, 98,5%"							000							012					012				012		012					012					012									
"L-Threonine, 98,5%"							003							009					009				009		009					009					009									
"L-Isoleucine, 98,5%"							003							011					011				011		011					011					011									
"L-Valine, 96,5%"							000							008					008				008		008					008					008									
"L-Tryptophan, 98%"							000							003					003				003		003					003					003									
"L-Arginine, 98,5%"							014							000					006				012		018					024					030									
Mineral Premix1							013							013					013				013		013					013					013									
Vitamin Premix2							015							015					015				015		015					015					015									
"Salinomycin, 12%"							006							006					006				006		006					006					006									
BHT3							001							001					001				001		001					001					001									
"Crude Protein, %"							"2,077"							"1,904"					"1,904"				"1,904"		"1,904"					"1,904"					"1,904"									
"Metabolizable energy,"																																												
"kcal/kg                            3,200"														3.200					3.200				3.200		3.200					3.200					3.200									
"Calcium, %                                 0.760"														"0,760"					"0,760"				"0,760"		"0,760"					"0,760"					"0,760"									
"Phosphorus available, %           0.380"														"0,380"					"0,380"				"0,380"		"0,380"					"0,380"					"0,380"									
"SID Arginine, %                         1.203"														"0,940"					"1,000"				"1,060"		"1,120"					"1,180"					"1,240"									
"SID Lysine, %                            1.124"														"1,000"					"1,000"				"1,000"		"1,000"					"1,000"					"1,000"									
"1Trace mineral premix provided per kg of diet: Mn, 58.36 g; Fe, 41.68 g; Zn, 54.21 g; Cu,"																																												
"8.31 g; I, 0.84 g; Se, 0.25 g."																																												
"2Vitamin premix provided per kg of diet: vitamin A, 9,638,000 IU; vitamin D3, 2,410,000 IU; vitamin E, 36,100 IU; vitamin B1, 2.60 g; vitamin B2, 6.45 g; vitamin B6, 3.61 g; vitamin B12,"																																												
"15.9 mg; vitamin K3, 1.94 g; pantothenic acid, 12.95 g; nicotinic acid, 39.20 g; folic acid, 0.90 g; biotin, 89.80 mg."																																												
3Antioxidant Butylhydroxytoluene.																																												
"Table 3. Means of average daily feed intake (ADFI), body weight (BW), body weight gain"																																												
(BWG) and feed conversion ratio (FCR) of broilers fed diets with different SID Arg:Lys ratios																																												
                 and control diets in trials 1 and 2.                                                                                                                 																																												
SID Arg: Lys ratio (%)                                                  P value                     SEM																																												
Traits																																												
94         100        106       112       118       124     Control    ANOVA       Lin        Quad																																												
Trial 1 – From 01 to 21 days old																																												
"1,173"	"1,154"			"1,147"			"1,175"				"1,160"				"1,176"					"1,183"				"0,394"				-						-				"0,006"						
0.944*	0.955*			0.959*			"0,982"				"0,983"				"0,999"					"1,001"				<0.001				<0.001						"0,890"				"0,004"						
0.907*	0.918*			0.922*			"0,945"				"0,946"				"0,961"					"0,963"				<0.001				<0.001						"0,883"				"0,004"						
1.294*	"1,257"			"1,246"			"1,243"				"1,227"				"1,239"					"1,228"				"0,038"				"0,038"						"0,096"				"0,006"						
Trial 2 – From 22 to 44 days old																																												
"3,994"	"4,045"			"4,103"			"4,058"				"4,033"				"4,061"					"4,019"				"0,702"				-						-				"0,016"						
3.263*	3.305*			"3,411"			"3,427"				"3,422"				"3,466"					"3,477"				<0.001				<0.001						"0,146"				"0,015"						
2.307*	2.347*			"2,451"			"2,468"				"2,464"				"2,507"					"2,518"				<0.001				<0.001						"0,157"				"0,015"						
1.732*	1.724*			1.674*			"1,645"				"1,637"				"1,623"					"1,598"				<0.001				<0.001						"0,328"				"0,008"						
ADFI																																												
(kg) BW1																																												
(kg) BGW2																																												
(kg) FCR3																																												
(kg/kg)																																												
ADFI																																												
(kg) BW4																																												
(kg) BGW5																																												
(kg) FCR6																																												
(kg/kg)																																												
* Means followed by an asterisk on the same line differ from the control group by Dunnett’s																																												
test (P≤0.05).																																												
1Y = 0.7727857 + 0.0018119X; R² = 0.96.																																												
2Y = 0.7354857 + 0.0018119X; R² = 0.96.																																												
3Y = 1.4425562 – 0.0017557X; R² = 0.72.																																												
4Y = 2.6661500 + 0.0065710X; R² = 0.86.																																												
5Y = 1.7135690 + 0.0065160X; R² = 0.87.																																												
6Y = 2.1047260 – 0.0039650X; R² = 0.93.																																												
"Y is the response variable, and X is the SID Arg: Lys ratio. SEM = Standard Error of the Mean."																																												
Table 4. Means of creatine levels in muscle (CRM) and serum (CRS) of samples of breast																																												
and blood collected from broilers at 21 and 44 days old that were fed diets with different SID																																												
                          Arg:Lys ratios and control diets in trials 1 and 2.                                                                                          																																												
SID Arg: Lys ratio (%)                                                      P value                    SEM																																												
Traits																																												
94		100			106			112				118					124						Control			ANOVA						Lin					Quad							
																	Trial 1–21 d																											
0.151*		0.153*			0.160*			0.184*				"0,234"					0.265*						"0,223"			<0.001						<0.001					"0,001"					"0,006"		
																	Trial 2–44 d																											
"0,090"		"0,096"			"0,099"			0.110*				0.111*					"0,095"						"0,096"			<0.001						"0,008"					"0,001"					"0,002"		
926		977			"1,001"			"1,246"				"1,386"					"1,351"						"1,161"			<0.001						<0.001					"0,959"					"3,390"		
CRM1																																												
(ppm)																																												
CRM2																																												
(ppm) CRS3																																												
(μmol/L)																																												
* Means followed by an asterisk on the same line differ from the control group by Dunnett’s																																												
test (P≤0.05).																																												
1Y = -0.2448057 + 0.0040014X; R2 = 0.88.																																												
2Y = -0.6149000 + 0.0128300X – 0.00005454X2; R2 = 0.71.																																												
3Y = -71.918100 + 1.7129000X; R2 = 0.89.																																												
"Y is the response variable, and X is the SID Arg:Lys ratio. SEM = Standard Error of the Mean."																																												
Table 5. Means of skin thickness (ST) and skin strength (SS) of skin samples collected from																																												
broilers at 21 and 44 days old and were fed diets with different SID Arg:Lys ratios and control																																												
                  diets in trials 1 and 2.                                                                                                                                      																																												
SID Arg: Lys ratio (%)                                                   P value                    SEM																																												
Traits																																												
94         100        106        112        118        124      Contro																																												
ANOVA       Lin       Quad																																												
                                                                                                                   l                                                                      																																												
Trial 1–21 d																																												
ST1 (mm)			0.489*			0.537*			"0,622"				0.688*					0.815*				0.955*			"0,596"				<0.001						<0.001						"0,002"			"0,019"
SS (mm)			"8,269"			"9,111"			"10,478"				"9,820"					"9,088"				"7,928"			"9,320"				"0,108"						-						-			"0,264"
Trial 2–44 d																																												
ST2 (mm)			0.669*			0.861*			"0,898"				"1,063"					1.124*				1.211*			"0,990"				<0.001						<0.001						"0,159"			"0,024"
SS3 (mm)			4.545*			4.036*			5.154*				7.053*					"7,888"				"10,171"			"9,963"				<0.001						<0.001						"0,059"			"0,391"
* Means followed by an asterisk on the same line differ from the control group by Dunnett’s																																												
test (P≤0.05).																																												
1Y = -0.9921810 + 0.0153786X; R2 = 0.97.																																												
2Y = -0.9313000 + 0.0174500X; R2 = 0.97.																																												
3Y = -15.111120 + 0.1980300X; R2 = 0.90.																																												
"Y is the response variable, and X is the SID Arg:Lys ratio. SEM = Standard Error of the Mean."																																												
UNIVERSIDADE FEDERAL DE VIÇOSA																																												
COMISSÃO DE ÉTICA NO USO DE ANIMAIS DE PRODUÇÃO CEUAP/UFV																																												
"  Campus Universitário – Viçosa, MG – 36570-900 – Telefone:(31) 3899.3275 – e-mail: ceuap@ufv.br – site: www.ceuap.ufv.br                            "																																												
CERTIFICADO																																												
"Viçosa, 08 de fevereiro de 2021"																																												
"Certificamos que o projeto intitulado "": Relação arginina / lisina e de isoleucina / lisina para frangos"																																												
"de corte de 01 a 21 dias e de 22 a 46 dias de idade"", protocolo nº 01/2021, sob a responsabilidade de Luiz Fernando Teixeira Albino - que envolve a produção, manutenção e/ou utilização de animais pertencentes ao filo chordata, subfilo vertebrata (exceto o homem), para fins de pesquisa científica (ou ensino) - encontra-se deacordo com os preceitos da lei nº 11.794, de 8 de outubro de 2008, do decreto nº 6.899, de 15 de julho de 2009, e com as normas editadas pelo Conselho Nacional de Controle da Experimentação Animal (CONCEA), e foi apreciado pela Comissão de Ética no Uso de Animais de Produção da Universidade Federal de Viçosa (CEUAP- UFV) em reunião de 05 de fevereiro de 2021."																																												
Finalidade: (x)Pesquisa ( )Ensino Vigência do Projeto: de 10 de abril de 2021 a 10 de outubro de 2021 Espécie/linhagem: Frango de corte (Gallus domesticus)																																												
"Nº de animais: 2860           Peso: 0,04Kg            Idade: 01 dia           Sexo: Macho"																																												
"Origem: Incubatorio Rivelli CNPJ/CPF: 478.715.616-49 Endereço: Rua Leão José, 257 Mateus Leme, MG Responsável : Maria Cecília CRMV: 10595"																																												
CERTIFICATE																																												
"We certify that the project entitled ""Arginine / Lysine and Isoleucine / Lysine ratios to broilers from 1"																																												
"to 21 days and from 22 to 46 days"", protocol nº 01/2021, under the responsibility of Luiz Fernando Teixeira Albino - which involves the production, maintenance and/or use of animals belonging to the phylum chordata, subphylum vertebrata (except man), for scientific research purposes (or education) - is in accordance with the law nº. 11.794, of October 8, 2008, Decree nº. 6899 of July 15, 2009, and the rules issued by the Brazilian National Council for Animal Experimentation Control (CONCEA), and was approved by the Ethics Commission on the use of farm animals of Universidade Federal de Viçosa (CEUAP-UFV) in its meeting on Feb, 05th, 2021."																																												
Finality: ( x )Research         ( )Education																																												
"Duration of the Project: from Apr, 10th, 2021 a Oct, 10th, 2021"																																												
"Species / strain: Broiler (Gallus domesticus)       Nº of animals: 2860          Weight: 0,04 kg"																																												
"Age: 01 day Sex: Male Source: Incubatorio Rivelli CNPJ/CPF: 478.715.616-49 Endereço: Rua Leão José, 257 Mateus Leme, MG Responsável : Maria Cecília CRMV: 10595"																																												
Luciana Navajas Rennó																																												
Coordenadora da CEUAP/UFV																																												
